[Music]
in my video series starting with how to
get the weight loss benefits of a fedra
without the risks I noted how drinking
water affects the release of the adrenal
hormone noradrenaline making it the
safest metabolic booster for weight loss
and recommended drinking two cups of
cold water on an empty stomach a few
times a day ideally before meals is a
form of that negative calorie
pre-loading as I discuss in my video
evidence-based weight loss but what
about just staying hydrated in general
in a national survey one of the weight
control practices most associated with
successful weight loss was drink plenty
of water but it was also associated with
unsuccessful attempts at weight loss
it's just one of the most popular weight
loss tips across the board both in the
mainstream media and a common
recommendation given to patients by
their positions but does it work can we
just Add Water about a dozen Studies
have been published on the matter and
overall there does appear to be a weight
reducing benefit to increased water
consumption what's the obvious
confounder though uh confounding factors
also known as lurking variables are some
third element that ends up being the
true explanation for a supposed length
between two things here's a textbook
example there may be a tight correlation
between ice cream sails and drowning
deaths but that doesn't mean ice cream
causes drowning a more likely
explanations that there's a lurking
third variable like hot weather
summertime that explains why drowning
deaths are highest when ice cream
consumption is at its peak so what might
be a confounding factor that offers an
alternate explanation of why those who
drink more tend to lose more
weight maybe it's because those who
drink more water tend to drink less soda
so maybe the reason more water is
associated to more weight loss is
because there's the third variable a
confounding variable like less soda
consumption connected to both and that's
the real cause the primary reason that
the CDC USDA American Medical
Association American Diabetes
Association American Heart Association
and American Academy of Pediatrics all
recommend drinking water for weight
management is as a replacement of
beverages with calories even replacing
one sugary beverage or beer with water
per day is associated with a lower
incidence of obesity over time American
Children and adolescents drink so much
soda that replacing all sugary beverages
with water could result in an average
reduction of 235 calories a day and what
about exercise that's another obvious
confounder candidate after all who
drinks a lots of water those who spend
hours working out so no wonder water
drinkers might be slimmer
a study of dieting overweight women took
both soda and exercise into account and
still however found a benefit associated
with increased water consumption over a
year those who drink at least a liter a
day of water lost about five more pounds
on average than those who didn't the
researchers were able to control for
physical activity and intake of other
beverages but what about other Foods it
turns out that those who drink more
water also tend to eat more fruits and
vegetables Greens and Beans and whole
grains and total sugar and less fast
food no wonder they're healthier weight
to control for dietary factors the
scientific world had to bring out the
big guns Harvard's big cohort studies
that follow the diets and health have
more than 100,000 doctors and nurses for
decades they were able to control not
just for other Beverages and lifestyle
factors such as exercise smoking
sleeping and TV watching but a wide
range of healthy and unhealthy food
intakes from fruits and vegetables to
meat candy consumption they were the
first to show that increasing water
intake per se was independently and
significantly associated with less
weight gain over the long term
consumption patterns in these studies
were by self-report though prents were
just asked to fill out detailed
questionnaires about their diet for more
of an objective measure researchers
directly assess people's hydration
status by assessing their blood and
urine concentrations in both adults
and children the more hydrated people
were the less likely they were to be
obese spot checking urine from nearly
10,000 men and women research found that
nearly half of obese individuals were
walking around under hydrated compared
to fewer than one and three individuals
who were normal weight or
lighter uh the problem with snapshot in
time studies is you don't know which
came first did underhydration lead to
obesity or did obesity lead to under
hydration at a heavier weight you
actually need more water the daily water
requirements of a man of average height
weighing 210 lb may actually be four
cups more than the same man at 160 lb
and who's more hydrated those who eat
more water-rich foods like fruits and
vegetables there's that Spectre of
confounding again the only way to prove
cause and effect is to put it to the
test in an inter conventional trial
which I'll cover next
[Music]